I was saying I would always first when I
first met her I was gonna be first up
today I was slightly Dario because quite
frankly I didn't love the responsibility
of saying it out but all day but the
more I thought about it the more I
thought that actually what I've got to
say might provide a really useful
context for everything else that is
going to follow and I hope also it might
provide a couple of potential solutions
for the experience of powerlessness and
you know what can the individual do that
sort of feeling that I think is pretty
prevalent among activists so I think as
actually is what we try and do and we're
trying to change a system that is both
pervasive and very very protective of
itself what we need to find is a point
of access point a point of attack
something that I like to think of it as
a nexus point which is connected to
everything else rather than if you can
weaken that just like a main structure
and abilities you can weaken that it
brings the whole thing down and I think
peanut Josephina zeitgeist movies did an
excellent idea of identifying money as
that nexus point and I came away from
watching the addendum three or four
years ago whenever it was thinking might
go to actually understand for the first
time just how profoundly and
systemically corrupt our institutions
are and how it's money that lies right
at the heart of it and so you know I
fight when tilting at windmills share to
give anyone would listen going down to
speaker's corner and I was pretty
convinced at the time that all you would
have to do is explain it clearly to
people
and once they realize just how
fraudulent it was and how much it
actually enslaves us as a society that
you know that that's all that would be
required to bring change about but I
realized how that was pretty naive and
you know the thing is though even if you
do manage to get it across the salon you
do manage to convince them that they do
see it for what it is what's the
individual's supposed to do the
individual stands powerless against
systems like the financial system the
against systems like the governmental
system the corporatocracy
you know the individual stance powers
and so I think many of us feel after a
very short time a sense of frustration
that we can see what's wrong with the
world but we can't see
what to do about it and that's kind of
what I want to address in this talk
because I've come to realize that
there's a level deeper than money and it
is more powerful because it's deeper but
it is also more accessible to us as
individuals to do something about and
that level I'm talking about sort of got
late when I diagrams the metaphysical
substrate and by the metaphysical
substrate what I mean is the stories and
myths and narratives that we tell each
other to bind society together and that
is a point of attack that we as
individuals and small groups can make a
deal that can make a real difference to
it because our social systems grow out
of a metaphysical substrate so if you
can change the substrate the systems
will change as a consequence of that so
I want to focus on in this talk three
things firstly I want to get across to
you just how powerful stories and myths
are in affecting how we act in this
world Harry orient ourselves in this
world I then want to go on and look at
some of the prevailing stories and makes
and narratives that exist in our society
and show that they are bad stories and
that they are bad stories because they
route us in what you'll call the shadow
and I want to introduce you for those of
you who don't already know about it to
the idea of Jung's shadow and then the
last part of my talk is going to be
about Joseph Campbell's hero's journey
because I think that's very relevant to
all of us if we can see ourselves as
being on that hero's journey
it is a motivator and it gives us a
sense of making a real and meaningful
contribution to the change that we want
to see in the world so to begin with I'm
going to tell you a little story just to
get across here there's gonna be the
first thing of my talk is the power of
story and I can see no better way of
doing that than by example so Tony Tony
little story once upon a time there was
a colony of mussels and they lived on
the river bed and they climbed to the
river bed and the water rushed past them
and all day every day they cling to each
other and they cling to the rocks and
they filter food out of the water
and all knowing every night they think
of each other and they clean to the
rocks and they have a little sleep and
after a while one of the mussels starts
to get agitated and he goes around the
staff
today I wasn't saying is this really all
there is clinging to the rocks we need
to each other picking bits of food out
of Ottoman is this really all there is
an world world what do you mean well
what happens if we just let go what
happens if we just let go and let the
current take us you can't do that others
have tried you see those rocks down
there the current takes you smashes you
against the rocks there's nothing you
can do but after hearing this one he
just can't bear it anymore and so he
says it's goodbyes to his friends and
his family and he lets go and off he
goes and sure enough the client takes in
the wife bashes him against a couple of
the rocks round the bend of the river
and he disappears gone forever
now the story ends here is a pretty
disappointing story is there and it's a
really disappointing story because the
hero's dead right what else is there the
hero's dead and I want to come back to
this place run the importance of the
hero's journey because it's deep deep
deep in our psyche this this unfolding
of a plot and so but anyway this is not
the end of the story what actually
happens is that as the muscle rams the
baby took a couple of knocks on the rock
but that's what shells are for right so
not seriously damaged and as the river
rounds the baby opens up widens the
current slows down and he experiences
all sorts of things he gets involved in
a scene group with some clams and he
meets all sorts of other creatures that
he's never seen before
and eventually he finds a place if he
likes you guys are sure and he settles
down this is a pretty short simple even
somewhat silly story but even within
every single one of you has taken a
couple of little morals messages away
from that right I mean I'd like to poll
the room I don't have that kind of time
there's a lot of stuff I want to go
through today and I do want to stick to
my half ounce so I won't do that but you
know a couple of things you might take
from it is for example to risk
everything in search of adventure is a
noble goal in life well you might see it
from the other mothers perspective say
well actually these are band and his
friends and his family they don't have
him to claim to at night
he's left them poorer by disappearing
off like that or a level deeper than
that you might think well perspective is
everything right because remember from
the perspective of the muscles he left
behind he was smashed against the rocks
and was killed so you know our many many
clients as a term sure there's many
people come up with many different many
different interpretations but the point
is you get into it straight away right
you can't help yourself straight away
something about the story captures you
you live out the story as though you
were one of the characters in it and
then so it affects you not just on a
mental on an intellectual level but on
an emotional level and even on a
spiritual level as well brain scans
indicate that when you're exposed to
factual information only once we regions
of your brain might have but where
you're exposed to marriage it when
you're exposed to storytelling multiple
regions of your brain lights up at the
same time to give you an even more
concrete example that kondeh significant
objects tone okay so other one be
organizing the study dude was they
employed the services of 200 writers and
they sense these 200 rights go out to
bric-a-brac shop junk shops whatever and
buy something anything for a couple of
bucks and then put it up on eBay and try
and sell it but before selling it right
a little story about it to give the
object some significance in the in the
minds of the people that are looking at
the at the ads so these 200 writers
spent between them at home with two
hundred and fifty dollars on acquiring
musical objects and sold them on eBay
for just shy of eight thousand dollars
so this is another little example of
just how powerful stories can be at
grabbing our attention so what are ways
so powerful and Ewing has a great deal
to say about this I don't have time to
go deeply you know in theory obviously
but I would like to just touch on it
okay
couple of context so these are the
twelve archetypes that you came up with
and what is what these are are kinds of
characters that you use in order to act
in the world because we've got two parts
of ourselves that need to be reconciled
we have our sense of being people being
organisms being consciousnesses but we
also have to act in the external world
and to reconcile these two things we
create these characters and we tell
ourselves a story and we become the lead
characters in that story and this sense
of characterization of narrative and an
unfolding plot in our life is very very
fundamental so how we how we apprehend
the world and how we make sense of it
there's an infinite amount of
information out there which we have to
sort that make sense of and try and turn
that into an interpretation of the world
which is manageable and hopefully
ultimately meaningful I was hoping to do
this without notes at all I brought my
bottle down and I brought them on with
me anyway but yeah I just want to get to
where I am on my four pages into my
notes now so when it gets where I am
okay so I'll come back I'll talk a
little bit more about Union stuff in a
minute this guy here you've all know if
there are many of you may have read this
book or there's anyone in the room I can
see a few people nodding it's a really
excellent book if you haven't read in
this book he talks about the three great
revolutions in the evolution of the
civil of the human civilization the
cognitive revolution we started 71
thousand years ago then the agricultural
about 12,000 years ago and then the
scientific most recently starting about
five hundred years ago and the cognitive
revolution is when language and art
appeared for the first time and this
also allowed for the first time for
stories and myths to take hold to become
more complex to become much more widely
disseminated and because they became
more complex and more adept larger
numbers of people were able to buy into
them and these stories are absolutely
essential because they allow for much
more widespread collaboration would
otherwise be possible many of you may
have heard of Robin Dunbar is
he's a psychologist and anthropologists
that modeling college upstate he did a
study where he compared frontal cortex
size to the number of relationships that
an organism could hold if I actually
front of all his frontal quarters in
relation to ogle brain anyway doesn't
matter and the number he came up for
humans with one hundred and forty seven
point eight 150 relationships is the
maximum that a single human being can
maintain and so unless there are larger
stories to buy into societies can never
grow beyond about backside 150 indeed
the maximum number of people you can
know even at the most rudimentary level
are you putting a name to a face is
about 1,500 and we're obviously living
in societies of millions hundreds of
millions even billions of people now and
so these cultural stories are absolutely
essential to the cohesion of these
larger societies so the point about the
next question is well all the stories
that we're using to bind our society
gather together excuse me are they
useful are they helpful
are they constructive so nice take a
look at some of them here's our old
friend money right what does money bring
about what money brings about selfish
behavior it brings about a sense of
disconnectedness from the true value of
things and artificial sense of
competition between people the need to
chip off each other in these to scarcity
which in turn leads to miss mistrust in
society which that decaying social
institutions that they can no longer be
funded and greed above all because what
is greed really other than a fear of
scarcity in the future why would you
hoard stuff unless you're worried that
sometime down the road you're not going
to have enough right so greed is
actually really something very
reasonable long-term security but it
gets out of control
when prompted by things like money
scarcity already gone through nationhood
I mean I'll just a few minutes look at
this slide because this pretty much
encapsulate what I want to say
I think it's really good this was doing
around on space was going to a while ago
I think it's really excellent but I mean
I think you can summarize this as
nation's lead to war and lead to
suspicion of the other races probably
the other way around right suspicion of
the other which in turn leads to war
then we have our old friends religion
and God no religion and God is that
removes a sense of personal
responsibility removes the need to
question things impedes your ability to
learn anything because well hey I can't
go against what I've been told is true
separates us from nature leads to guilt
the concept of sin you know there's a
long list I know I not really here to go
through all that I just want to look at
snow you know take a brief overview of
some of the main stories that we use in
our society material science is one of
the newest for the most pervasive
stories that exist and what a material
science tell that tells us where
machines if your machines then you treat
each other as machines it teaches us
that the world is just a bunch of stuff
out there for us to use any way that we
wish to and so despite the fact that
these things are killing us in the long
run these stories are actually more real
these cultural myths these problems are
more real to us than the real world I
mean just as a trivial example how many
people know the Koch logo versus what an
oak leaf looks like you know I mean yeah
this artificial world of stories that
we've created for ourselves is more real
than the actual real world and and we
cling to them despite the fact that it's
going to end up killing us I love this
picture again I'll just give you a
minute to read this before I go on to my
next point which is talking about the
shadow
and so like I said we're living in bad
stories and these stories are bad
because they encourage us to live in
shadow by that I mean these are the
twelve archetypes that I head up on that
colored wheel earlier on when those
archetypes well realize when those
archetypes are lived in truth when those
archetypes are lived in the light these
are the qualities that each of those
archetypes brings to the table brings
into the world
however when their archetype lives in
fear when their archetype lives in
shadow this is what manifests in the
world instead I take a look at the red
list take a look at the black with what
do you feel more of in this world today
the shadow is rooted entirely in fear
and denial and I think a really good way
of summarizing what the shadow is this
is a choir I think this is Ewing himself
saying all that you are not you also are
now the shadow is those repressed bits
of either you don't like to read that
they don't like to acknowledge are there
for example if you think of yourself as
a kind and generous and compassionate
and decent person who doesn't like to
upset others then you may very well find
it as a consequence of maintaining that
self-image when you're faced with a
situation that demands of you forthright
and assertive behavior that you are
insufficiently forthright and assertive
as a consequence of that you start to
feel bitterness and resentment and this
builds up over time but you don't really
want to face it because it goes against
your image of yourself and so it's
really gated to the shadow doesn't mean
it doesn't exist none of us are free of
our shadows but until you start to learn
to integrate your shadow you cannot be
an effective agent of change in this
world and we are forced to live by the
systems that we endure we are forced to
live predominantly in shadow and it's up
to individuals to realize that fact find
a way to integrate their shadow so that
they can be more effective agents that
positive change in this world this is
just another quick driver I'm not going
to spend long on this but this is the 12
archetypes properly realized in the
light these are
shadows when expressed through when
expressed in Chan or expressed through
fear so the patriarchy becomes the
dictator the angel becomes the victim
the magician becomes the sorcerer and
you see is that it's a similar idea but
turned on its head there's a model that
I kind of like better these guys here
Robert Moore in Douglas Dillard wrote
this book king or a magician lover it's
the same idea it's a very young young
concept but they distilled the 12
Jungian archetypes down to four namely
those ones and their concept of the
shadow is kind of easier to get your
head around in some ways their concept
of the shadow is that the when you live
in sharing or living in one or other of
the polar opposites which when
transcended and United make up the
properly Express archetype and again
once again just very quickly look at the
bottom line look at the top line what do
you see more of in this world
more masculine archetypes well these are
masking of the top feminine of the box
and that's that's that's how this is
broken down yes I would agree I think
broadly that's true yes absolutely
absolutely but on you know that they do
make a point in the book of masculine
feminine do not reside entirely in men
and women you know what I mean of the
masculine and feminine resides in both
men and women again obviously the
minotaur kind of made this point
one does not become enlightened but I
imagine Inc leaders like well I met that
by making the darkness conscious this
guy here is another guy that really
influenced my thinking about Charles
Eisenstein he's a natural philosopher
the stories that I saw through earlier
money nation religion etc etc etc he
groups those and many many other of our
cultural narratives under the umbrella
of what he calls the story of separation
that all of these stories are designed
or have have become whether designed or
not have had have come about to separate
us from each other to separate us from
the natural world to disconnect us from
our power to disconnect us from our
knowledge of who we are and there are
two ideas of his in particular I would
just like to acquaint you with very
quickly the first is the idea of the
opener so the of the gifting economy
here you turned the whole idea in
economy on its head and so at the moment
things I mentioned earlier on greed is
hoarding due to fear of scarcity in the
future and that provides you with some
security of security and a gift economy
cultural in fact that you know that
whatever you need is out there are
people and people are happy to give it
to you just as you are happy to give
whatever you are able to give to the
world and your status and value in
society is now perceived not by how much
you have but by how much you give it
turns the whole thing up on its head the
other idea he talked about which I
really like is the idea of peaks of
understanding and that the current
narratives that we've been using in
society have taken us as high as they
can possibly take us they are flawed and
they take us as far as they can possibly
take us and that people are becoming
aware of the fact that there's a better
peak of understanding over there but in
order to get from here to there you've
got to go and down into the valley in
order to ascend the next peak right and
that this is one of the main barriers
holding us back is that people are
fearful of descending into the valley
because in the valley is the unknown in
the valley you have to face the dragon
and only when you face the dragon can
you grab the treasure and enter the
world as a meaningful agent of change
and this is this is the final theme of
my talk is the hero's journey as
described by this guy Joseph Campbell
Joey Campbell spent his whole life
studying mythologies from all over the
world and when he was particularly
looking for with similarities and
differences between those mythologies
and he would attribute similarities to
elements of our psyche which are common
to all human beings everywhere you know
rooted in our biology and is not
cultural and and the differences in the
narratives he attributed to cultural
influences and so themes like slaying
the dragon themes like resurrection
themes like the wise mentor these appear
all over the world across vast time
spans completely independently of each
other with no possibility of these
groups having communicated with each
other and so I think it's reasonable to
assume that these these are themes which
reside deep in our psyche according to
the archetypes of those that I went
through earlier with you this is a sort
of circular representation of the hero's
journey he's written a whole book about
this which I highly recommend you read
it's both inspirational and educational
this is a much simplified version of I'm
gonna use this one it's just very
quickly like I said I have a huge amount
of time lots of ideas and to talk you
through it so the beginning of the
hero's journey is right here this is the
call to adventure and I'm assuming that
most of you are in this room right now
because you have experienced that right
you've felt that call to adventure
that's why you're here right now and
wondering what you can actually do to
bring meaningful positive change to the
world the call is sometimes refused for
whatever reason it might be fear it
might be circumstances of your life
whatever it may be but around about here
this is the important transition you're
transiting from the ordinary world into
the special world and your transition
through the special world if this is the
process of death and rebirth this is the
resurrection the story of the
resurrection comes this is the idea
underlying the story of resurrection is
when you cross the threshold you then
encounter resources both within yourself
and outside yourself that you never knew
you had you are tested you meet people
who are going to help you and when you
are on a hero's journey because this is
something which resides deep in the
psyche of every single one of us when
you are on your hero's journey other
people recognize that you're on the
hero's journey and they
stand ready to help you because they you
know whether consciously or not they
realize that that's what you're doing
and they stand ready to help but the
final deal is your confrontation with
the dragon but what does the dragon
guard the dragon guards the treasure and
having seized the treasure from the
dragon shaking off your shadow overcome
your inner demon whatever it might be it
doesn't have to be the hero's journey
can be gone through many times in one
lifetime the hero's journey does not
have to be as dramatic as the trials of
Perseus right you know the hero's
journey can be much more mundane than
there but you really after the special
world reborn as a new version of
yourself
ready to undertake the task we called
you to adventure in the first place
you see what I mean and I think
conceptualizing yourself as being on
that hero's journey heeding the call to
action making sacrifices enduring
unbearable hardships discovering
resources in your stuff that you never
knew you'll happen that you never knew
you had only to emerge victorious
nothing slaying the dragon back into the
worlds are much better version of
yourself it's an inspirational thing and
it could provide motivation when you're
thinking that you know really nothing
that nothing seems to be changing I
don't know how many of you have seen
infinity where I love this film it made
it made by far by far the best of
reliable movies the reason I bring it up
here have you just discussed the hero's
journey I mean anyone that's watching
most of people I suppose he wasn't
really felt a great deal of sympathy for
them I didn't hate them it wasn't a bad
guy right I understood where he was
coming from and the reason for that is
that that loss is on the hero's journey
you think about what else goes through
call-to-action great sacrifice you know
what I mean in others so that is very
very much on the hero's journey just
like Thor is Thor and Thanos go through
very very similar stages in their
journeys in infinity war this is a
YouTube channel that I came across I've
almost become very interested in stories
of mythology in the last year or so and
this is a really fantastic YouTube
channel what he does is he looks at
modern movies through the lens of
archetype and story and methought
and I just want to show you would
seemingly take cloud APIs is one of my
absolute favorite all-time uber and he
does a beautiful analysis of cloud APIs
and how beauty will save the world bruh
dasa t is the main source of conflict in
Cloud Atlas it is reflected in the
stories of each of the characters as
they struggle against greed power
malevolence and all the other qualities
that lead to victors and victims
oppressors and oppressed reflected by
the simple man through the weak and the
strong if we take the interconnectedness
of the stories into account there
appears to be a demoralizing truth to
this statement for although the
individual stories and with the main
characters achieving some form of
victory over the oppressing forces
they're facing on the larger cosmic
scale these victories feel radder income
sequential as the progress made in each
story is diminished by a new form of
oppression in the next there is a
natural order to this world and those
who try to upend it do not fare well it
raises a serious issue for moral
behavior on the individual level for why
should I suffer and sacrifice for a
greater good that's never going to
manifest itself why should I stand
against injustice if my efforts will
only end up being inconsequential here
Solzhenitsyn writes if only it were all
so simple if only there were evil people
somewhere insidiously committing evil
deeds and it were necessary only to
separate them from the rest of us and
destroy them but gradually it was too
close to me that the line separating
good and evil passes not through States
nor between classes nor between
political parties either but right
through every human heart at this point
in my life all I know six myth is that
this world spins from the same unseen
forces
the twist our hearts we can't expel evil
and injustice on this grand cosmic scale
we can constrict it within our own art I
owe my life to herself freed slave and I
cannot in good conscience participate in
this kind of business any longer yeah we
do have agency and we can make a
difference but we ourselves are
responsible to assume it and this takes
courage and honesty which at last brings
us to the purpose of art against eternal
injustice art offers beauty as it's
equally eternal antidote it is difficult
to define what this beauty is but this
is exactly the point it is up to you to
do it you have to bring your own agency
to it and define what it is Solzhenitsyn
wrote that one drop of truth cannot
weigh an ocean of lies - which Cloud
Atlas adds what has an ocean put a
multitude of crops it emphasizes that it
only takes one drop to preserve goodness
and justice within a limitless ocean the
existence of this drop is not a lost
cause it is all that matters and so
Cloud Atlas makes its case for how the
human heart over and over again will
save the world in its entirety it
doesn't give you a definitive moral path
but it does urge you to take up the
responsibility to find one for yourself
to stop doing the things that make you
feel weak and stand up for what is truly
meaningful to be that one drop in the
ocean
I've kind of alluded to this is a great
quote from Bobby Kennedy the point is
that by living more harmoniously more
generously more kindly in the world by
forming little collaborations with those
people around you form little islands
within this desert of shadow he formed
in islands of life and you inspire other
people to inform their to form a little
islands bright and those in line of
signs that overlap with each other and
before you know it you've created a new
culture because all the culture is is
the stories and interactions that go on
in the people that exist with it in so
each and every individual has a very
real and a very meaningful role to play
in change from a cultural substrate that
I mentioned at the start of this but so
just to finish with one final story
there's a story about an old man who
likes to go fishing and so every day he
goes down to the seawall and he sits on
the seawall and he catches a couple of
fish he takes them home to his family
comes to love them even together into
doing this for usually isn't very good
he's a very simple life and he's sitting
on a ball fishing one day when a tourist
and a boat rose by them and they get
talking and the story says to him say
come down here if anyone you know you
must know the fishing pretty well there
wanna brag of course so why do you catch
for my notification you know sell them
in growth by yourself and then you catch
even more fish you know anything you
could make a nice living fear so okay
and then what would I do well you know
if you wanted to buy a boat you could
start employing people you know you keep
their answer makes your production and
then what would I do
well once you've got enough money you
don't have to do anything it's all
very efficient so again a simple little
story but one final thought before I
leave you the two little stories that
are floating the muscle story and the
old man's story and the two new
characters that you identify with this
in the first one if you think about that
the muscle is going on a journey right
has to go on a journey can't bear to
stay where he is in the second story got
the exact opposite man doesn't want to
go on any kind of a journey is very very
content and very lengthy where he is and
so you know neither of these things are
right interviews things are wrong with
identifiable characters because we see
validity in both of those perspectives
the reason we like both of these
characters the reason they are the
heroes in us in these stories is because
they are doing what they do they making
the choices that they make in the full
knowledge of what they are doing what
they are sacrificing and what they are
gaining and making those choices and
taking complete responsibility for doing
so our society encourages the exact
opposite kind of behavior does not
encourage us to say responsibility
there's no encourages to make positive
choices and so my final clear I guess is
as individuals we need to every single
one of us work on getting out of the
shadow that society has pushed us into
and start creating those little islands
of life in the darkness so that they can
start connecting with each other and I
really do believe that it is at the
individual level and at the level of
story myth narrative changing the
cultural substrate from which the
system's ultimately grow I do think that
that is the most meaningful thing that
we as individuals and as small groups
can do and that's really what I have to
say thank you very